<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of Mr. Patrik Crawfurd his returne from poperie to the true religion, which is according to the Word of God, in holie Scripture</title>
            <author>Crawfurd, Patrick.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852333</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852333</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17649</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17649)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1134:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of Mr. Patrik Crawfurd his returne from poperie to the true religion, which is according to the Word of God, in holie Scripture</title>
                  <author>Crawfurd, Patrick.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wreittoun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some copies have an extra leaf with Latin verse addressed to the author by T. Crawfurd--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:1"/>
            <p>THE DECLARATION OF Mr. PATRIK CRAWFVRD HIS <hi>RETVRNE FROM POPERIE TO THE TRVE</hi> Religion, which is according to the Word <hi>of GOD, in holie Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Pſal. 40. verſe 2.</bibl>
            <q>He hath brought me vp out of an horrible pit, out of the myrie clay, &amp;c.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, Printed by <hi>Iohn Wr cittoun.</hi> Anno Dom. 1627.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honourable, the right Reverend, and worſhipfull, <hi>THE LORD PROVEST, BAILYIES, MINISTERS, AND</hi> remanent Counſellours of EDINBVRGH, all <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace heere and glorie heereafter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eeing obliged in conſcience, for the glorie of God, and edification of his People, to publiſh this my declaration of my returning to the true Religion, theſe reaſons amongſt others moued mee to dedicate the ſame vnto you, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Chriſtian People, and to you their reuerend Paſtours. Firſt, becauſe my ſinne in revolting from this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in my youthlyneſſe is ſo grieuous, (howſoeuer the Lord hath ſhowne mercie to me, knowing that I did it in ignorance) that it becomes mee, as publickly as I can, to declare my Repentance: and this I haue thought the readieſt meane for that purpoſe. Next, becauſe I haue done wrong to my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Countrie, and the Church in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo farre as I was able, in the matter of Religion, and ſpeciallie I haue done my uttermoſt endeuour to haue weakned the hands of ſundrie profeſſing the doctrine of the ſaid Church, and drawne them to the Romiſh Religion, wherewith for the time of that my ignorance, I was in conceite. And now beeing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my errour in ſome meaſure, the ſhorteſt courſe which I could ſee to repaire this wrong, was, that ſo to you ſome ſort of ſatiſfaction might bee giuen, and by you who are the moſt eminent and conſpicuous and large Church in this Land, others who from all partes reſort vnto you, might receiue the ſatiſfaction in like manner. Thirdly, becauſe your Paſtours
<pb facs="tcp:17649:3"/> beene the ſpeciall Inſtruments of GOD of my ſatiſfaction in ſuch ſcruples and doubtes of Religion, as I had and propounded to them, before I could renounce the groundleſſe Religion of poperie, and the men who mette mee, when I was ſeeking home as a forlorne Sonne to my Fathers houſe againe, as iuſtly I may now call my ſelfe. You I ſay, right reverend, were the men that mette mee, and mecklie poynted out the way, and went along with mee, convoying mee on my way: in whoſe dealing with mee I might haue ſeene my heauenly Fathers readineſſe to meete and embrace mee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſometimes I grant, I haue ſpoken of you, as others of the Romiſh Religion doe of you, and of all faithfull and learned Miniſters, only for the Religions cauſe. But then I knew you not. Now I haue found that you haue both learning and Loue, and if you and others of your Calling were knowne, as I know you, I put no queſtion many ſhould bee nothing aſhamed, but glad at their heart to forſake the puddle of humane Doctrine, and take them to the fountaine of the diuine Scriptures. Now then ſeeing you are Paſtours to me, and I by this meanes as one of your Flock, if ſo it may pleaſe your flocke and you, to account of ſuch a wandering ſheepe as I haue beene. To whom could I offer this teſtimonie of my Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance rather than to you Honourable and Chriſtian People, and to you their vigilant and reuerend Paſtours, whoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian diſpoſition makes mee to hope that this my offer ſhall bee accepted in good part.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in Chriſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Patrik Crawfurd.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:3"/>
            <head>GENTILI CHARISSIMO <hi>Patricio Crafordio, à</hi> Caſſilton, <hi>ex Synagoga</hi> Romanâ ad Eccleſiae Evangelicae <hi>ſocietatem reduci.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>Vod <hi>Latii</hi> illecebras ſcorti evitâris, &amp; aſtum<note place="margin">Apoc. 17. ibid. 19. 9. ibid. 18. 4. ibid. 21. 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>In ſua quo incautos retia dira trahit:</l>
               <l>Quod thalamos ſancti ſis invitatus ad agni,</l>
               <l>Dum venit in caſtos ſponſa pudica thoros:</l>
               <l>Quod <hi>Babyloniacam,</hi> Domino ſuadente, ruinam</l>
               <l>Effugis, in <hi>Solymae</hi> tecta nouata redux;</l>
               <l>Gratulor, immenſumque Dei miſerantis amorem</l>
               <l>Miror, inexhauſtas &amp; bonitatis opes.</l>
               <l>Tu quoque quod, lubrico erroris de tramite caeci</l>
               <l>Converſus, fratres ſic ſtabilire paras,</l>
               <l>Laudo piumque animum, gratamque in pectore mentem,</l>
               <l>Et cum candenti ſimplicitate fidem.</l>
               <l>O vtinam ſurdis aures, &amp; lumina caecis</l>
               <l>Aſſidue Dominus ſic tribuiſse velit.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Crafordius.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17649:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> DECLARATION <hi>OF</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PATRIK CRAWFURD HIS <hi>RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVRNE FROM POPERIE, TO THE</hi> true Religion, which is according to the Word <hi>of God in holy Scripture,</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>He hath brought mee vp out of an horrible pit; <hi>out of the myrie clay. &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 40. <hi>Ver.</hi> 7</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The mercy of God to a Sinner.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe ſixe yeares bygone I haue beene a ſtranger to God and his Word, and haue lyen in darkneſſe of Poperie, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reading the Scriptures for the right end, but only to picke out ſomething of them for contraverſie, whereby I might brangle with ſome colour and appearance theſe who makes the Lords Word the only rule of their Religion: euen as many moe Schollers than I, doe read them ſtill, who ſets themſelfe to maintaine Poperie, and oppugne the reformed Religion. But now the Lord God who is grati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous and mercifull to many that deſerues wrath, who is found often-times of them who ſeekes him not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or ſeeks him not the right way, hath opened my eyes by the power of his owne trueth and light, which I in my ignorance ſmothred downe, and keeped vnder in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and hath made mee vnderſtand now, that there is no Rocke whereon to reſt that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Soule
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17649:5"/> that ſeeks certaintie either of Religion, or of Salvation, but the holy Scripture, and that learned mens judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and writings, and the teſtimonie of the Church and publicke Preaching, and conference, and reading, and meditation, and prayer to God for the Spirit of Wiſedome and grace, are all but meanes to point out the Lambe of God that takes away the ſinnes of the World, and to finde out his will ſet downe in his Teſtament. So that I may now ſay truelie, the Lord hath brought mee out of an horrible and darke Pit, where the light of the Lords Word is hid, and put vnder a Buſhell, and out of the myrye and teugh clay of their errours, which defyled mee and held mee faſt, wherein J found no ground to reſt on, but ſunke deeper dayly, and ſhould haue drowned at laſt, had not the Lord pulled mee out, and ſet my feete vpon a Rocke, and ordered my goings. The ſumme of which worke of God, as I haue declared to ſundrie priuatly, and now of late publickly, in the Church of <hi>Irwing,</hi> before my admiſſion to the Lords Table there, the 26. of Auguſt, 1627. ſo J found my ſelfe oblidged to declare the ſame by write to all men if I could, and that ſo much the more, as I haue beene more wicked in the wrong way than ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, who haue beene ſeduced and drawne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the trueth as I was, for J hauing drunken in the errours of Poperie as faſt as I could at home, went ouer to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italie,</hi> and other parts; and by the ſpace of foure yeares, what by trauells, what by conference, what by ſtudying in the Colledges of Jeſuites, made my ſelfe as able as I could to defend Poperie, and oppoſe true Religion: and when I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17649:5"/> returned home did what I could to pervert others, and to confirme them that were ſeduced: and convoyed Jeſuits oftentimes where their purpoſe was to further their deſignes, ſometimes beeing diſaguiſed with them for feare of diſcouerie, to the hurt of many Souls (the Lord forgiue mee) for whoſe cauſe I doe write this my declaration, if poſſiblie it comming to their handes might bee a meane to cauſe them conſidder their wayes, and repent, and forſake their Idols, and turne to ſeeke the Lord Jeſus, <hi>who will teach all them</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James 1. 5, John 14 16.</note> 
                  <hi>the true way, who ſeekes the ſame by prayer of God through Chriſt alone,</hi> and ſo the woundes might bee healed in Gods mercie, which I helped to giue theſe Souls in my blind zeale: the recouerie againe of whoſe Souls without any detriment to their bodilie eſtate worldly, is and ſhall bee euer my deſire: only the Lord giue them Repentance, and make my Repentance dayly more fruitfull, that J may bee as truelie zealous for the trueth, as euer I was blinde forward againſt the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP, 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Iuſtice of God, giuing thoſe ouer to beleeue lyes, who will not learne the trueth.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſhow then the whole matter from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the glory of God, and edification of all who pleaſes to peruſe theſe preſentes without prejudice, J was brought vp in the Colledge of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> and did paſſe, my courſe vnder learned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17649:6"/> godly Maſters, who did their diligence to inſtruct both me and others in human Learning and Religion, as time wold ſuffer: but I in my youthlineſſe did not lay Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to heart, and therfore was juſtly puniſhed thereafter: for within halfe an yeere after I ended my courſe in the Colledge, I was infected with the errours of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, (ſo iuſt a thing it is with God to puniſhe the neglect of trueth with giuing ouer to errour that they may belieue lyes, who will not take paines to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the trueth) for an Papiſt of my acquaintance, who had beene out of the Countrie, a Scholler ſharpe enough, began to deale with mee, and put mee in queſtion and doubt, concerning the Religion profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo much the more eaſilie as I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it not at that time. Then when J ſhould haue ſought ſatiſfaction of my doubts at thoſe who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the trueth, before J had giuen any more eare to him that ſeduced mee, J lent my eare ſtill, and gaue credite to all that hee ſpake, without examination according to the Scriptures (ſo dangerous a matter is it to admit any grounds of Religion without trying them by the rule of Gods Word; whether they bee divine or not) and ſo he poſſeſſed mee, what by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, what by Books, what by conference with Prieſts and others, of theſe erroneous poſitions following.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that the Romane Church was the mother Church, only true Catholicke and Apoſtolicke.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. That the Scriptures did not containe all things needfull for Saluation, but was an vnperfect rule of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. And that traditions muſt bee ioyned therewith, which were of equall authoritie with the Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17649:6"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. That the Scripture was obſcure and dangerous to be read by laickes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. That to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> belonged to giue the ſenſe of it, and that their expoſition was as good as Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was iudge of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traverſies of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 7. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could not erre.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 8. That Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 9. And that all the Popes ſince, were his lawfull ſucceſſours, Chriſts Vicars, heads of the Church and had authoritie aboue the Scriptures, and that he bare the Keyes of Heauen, and could not erre in doctrine, and no Saluation without the Roman Church for any Soule, and ſuch like. Thoſe grounds I drunke in, ſuppoſing them all to bee true; wherevpon my minde was caſten open to belieue euery thing which they commanded mee to belieue; and whatſoeuer the Church did belieue, without any further exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. So J was receiued amongſt Papiſts, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their Maſſe, heere at home. Then beeing deſirous to haue further inſight in the Romiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, J went ouer to <hi>France,</hi> and ſtayed there a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, converſing with Jeſuits in their Colledges. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after J went to <hi>Rome</hi> to the head ſpring of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſtayed there ſome eight Monthes, but was forced to leaue it through ſickneſſe, and retiering to <hi>Weſt-Flanders,</hi> J ſtayed in a ſeminarie, and ſtudied in a Colledge of Jeſuites ſome two yeares, all which time I remained obedient to all their injunctions giuen vnto mee, and albeit many things occurred in my trauells, which perplexed my minde, making me
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17649:7"/> doubt of the courſe I was entered into, yet I ſmothred all downe, by the weight of theſe groundes, which J had laid downe in the beginning, and namelie, of this that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could not erre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The power of Deluſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Obſerued their Church-men of greateſt account and Wiſedome among them, to lay heauie burthens and grieuous to bee borne vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but they themſelues tooke litle paines in the buſineſſe. They profeſſed for the moſt parte volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie pouertie one by one; but the yearely Rents and common Purſe, whereof euery man was furniſhed as he had to doe was verie rich. I ſaw ſome of their Orders liue by begging and Almes, who would ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue forſaken the craft, if there had beene any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in that courſe, either of hunger or cold, more than they pleaſed to take vpon themſelues, and make ſhow of: Yet I thought their Church coulde not erre. They profeſſed to bee ſo retired from the Worlde, as they could thinke of nothing but Heauen, and yet tooke the moſt wittie courſes that could bee, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand all mens effaires, deſignes and diſpoſition, and then made uſe of them all as beſt ſerued their owne ends. They profeſſed humilitie, but laboured in effect to bee in honour and eſtimation by all, and were as impatient to bee deſpyſed as any man: their ſpeciall paines beeing imployed, to bring moe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17649:7"/> and moe vnder their ſubiection, vnder pretence of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them religious. Yet J thought ſtill their Church could not erre. I ſaw the Pope who calls himſelfe <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour, and his Cardinals busked in the greateſt riches, and worldly honour that can bee in the Earth, and in the meane time caſting the glory of the Apoſtles, the preaching of the Goſpell, at their heeles, as vnbeſeeming their Grandour. When the Pope came abroad hee was carried in a gorgeous Chaire, vpon foure mens ſhoulders, and all men as he went by, kneeled direct to the ground, in effect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored him, as one inveſted with Chriſts power and preheminence in the earth, and owner of Chriſts ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the World, as his Legat and Lieutenant, and ſo I honoured him amongs others my ſelfe. And yet I thought all well for this preſumption that the Church could not erre. I ſaw the Church men take direct courſes that the common-People ſhould never vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what they or themſelues were doing: for their Maſſes and publick ſervices all was done in an vnknown language to the People, and for their ordinare Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they inioyned for the moſt part to ſay them in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, though they vnderſtood not the ſame. (Indeed heere in <hi>Scotland,</hi> becauſe ſuch proceeding hath giuen diſtaſte to ſundrie by appearance, libertie is giuen to thoſe who pleaſe to haue them in the vulgare language elſe where J haue not ſeene this ſo ordinarly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) Next by all meanes they laboured that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-People either had not the Bible in their vulgare language, or elſe that they red it not, or if any read it, that they ſhould not preſume to take any part of it in any ſenſe contrare to the doctrine and practiſe of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17649:8"/> the Roman Church, but inſtead thereof, J ſaw they filled their heads and hands with Jmages and Beads <hi>Agnus Deis,</hi> meddals and reliques and bookes of Prayer to this Saint, and to that Saint, and the office of our Lady as they call the Virgine Mary, and the legends of ſuch and ſuch miracles done by Saints departed, as they alledge. Such ſtuffe as theſe a man trauelling will finde in mens houſes, but ſeldome or neuer the Bible, and oftner mention will he heare of the Virgine Mary, than of our Lord and Sauiour, and the faireſt Churches and Chappels you ſhall finde dedicate to the Virgine Mary, and to Saint Peter, and Saint Paul, &amp; others, ſome hee, ſome ſhee Saints, to whoſe Chapells and Churches, you ſhall finde dayly numbers going in Pilgrimage or viſitation and offering their offerings and Prayers before ſuch an Altar, to one Saint to keepe them from the Peſt, to another, to keepe them from the Ague, to this Saint, for their Kyne, to that Saint for their Horſes, in ſuch varietie as I cannot number: for there are particulare Saintes for all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, whom to, at ſeuerall times by Prayers and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, ordinarly they haue their recourſe to bee hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Yet I thought all well thinking the Romiſh Church could not erre. At <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe, I remarked a Church, whoſe Patrone (if I remember) is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called in vulgare ſpeach, Saint Aloy, and hath power, as they ſay, to heale Horſes, or keep them from their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. To this Church once in the yeere all the Horſes of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Popes horſes and Cardinals, Counſellours and Citizens horſes are brought, and when they come to the Fount where the holy water ſtands, I ſaw one of the Prieſts ſprinkle holy water on the horſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17649:8"/> and another Prieſt receiue the offering that vſeth to be giuen at that time; by which meanes that Church and all theſe that waite vpon it are vpholden, and thus it is done in other places, and for ſeuerall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of men and beaſtes. All this J approued, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could not erre. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe <hi>I</hi> ſpeake theſe things without pittie of the eſtate of the poore Soules ſo abuſed: for J my ſelfe who had ſeene better thinges, and ſhould haue had better vnderſtanding, as a ſcholler, by tying my ſelfe without further warrand, to beleeue as the Church beleeues, and beleeuing the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could not erre, for that time allowed or forced my minde to allow of all theſe abominable Idolatries, and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of falſe Gods, and was as buſie to pray to all the Saints as any man, and ſaid my Prayers, <hi>Pater noſter, Ave Marie,</hi> and <hi>Confiteor</hi> vpon my beids, as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as the moſt ignorant old Wife among them. J keeped conſtantly the Matines and Veſpers, and Salute, ſaid the office of the dead, my long letanies and my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I approued their making of holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, conſecrating of meddals, beads. <hi>Agnus Deis &amp;c.</hi> Alſo that there was ſome divine vertue in making the ſigne of the Croſſe before my breaſt, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling the Deuill for the time from me, I beleeued I was as cleane as glaſſe, when the Prieſt did ſhrive and abſolve mee. I haue come with others to meete a proceſſion of ſundrie ſorts of Church men, carying a conſecrated hoſtie, which they did relate was Chriſt himſelfe, carried throughout the ſtreetes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> J haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len downe before it, worſhiped and adored it, with many others ſuppoſing it was Chriſt bodilie preſent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17649:9"/> when I was preſent at Maſſe I did the ſame vpon the ſame preſumption, J beheld the bread of the hoſtie before it was conſecrate as they call it, I beheld it when it was conſecrated, and when it was lifted vp, I ſaw bread as clearly as J ſaw the Prieſts hand that held it vp, J opened my mouth, and the Prieſt put it in my mouth, I ſaw btead with my eyes, I ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, J felt it, I taſted and diſcerned it as ſenſiblie as ever I did bread in my life, yet I beleeued that it was not bread, but Ieſus Chriſt corporally preſent, put in my mouth, and going downe my bellie, though all ſenſes (which God hath euer made the faithfull witneſſes of all miraculous changes whereof we read in Scripture) did teſtifie the contrare, I gaue them all the lye, becauſe I beleeued as the Church beleeued, and belieued that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could not erre. Thus I who would not beleeue the Trueth, was giuen ouer to ſuch fearefull ſuperſtition and ſtrong deluſion, that J might beleeue lyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>No end in erring, except the Lord reclaime.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe things were common to mee, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Romiſh Religion, but J went yet further than the common courſe, and was yet more beſotted by this deluſion, for I haue beene clark to the maſſe, helped the Preiſt to the ſaying of it, lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the maſſe Booke, now from the right hand to the left, now from the left to the right backe againe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17649:9"/> Now kneeling, now ſtanding, now bowing and ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the body, now knocking on my breaſt, now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſigne of the croſſe at the eleuation. I haue born vp the Prieſts taile with the one hand, hauing a burning torch in the other hand, ſometimes giuing him Wine and water in a Chalice, ſometimes one thing, ſometimes another, as ſuch like ſervice did require. I entred my ſelf yet further in their ſnare, and became one of the ſodalitie of our Lady. (<hi>This ſodalitie tyes none to any Eccleſiaſticall order, for therein with their approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, all Rankes of Perſons may be, ſo they uſe their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar devotion to our Lady</hi>) which is an ordour wherein eſpeciallie all devout ſtudents in Colledges by a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne oath and invocation of the Virgine Mary are tyed to vſe ſpeciall deuotion all their dayes to her, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her name, where euer they come, and to depend vpon her as their Lady Patroneſſe, and lady aduocate with God for them. O fearefull Idolatrie! and yet I ſwalowed it then, beleeuing as the Church beleeued, and that ſhe could not erre, and obeying as diuine truth what their Church commanded.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all J was in tearmes with the Ieſuits to haue ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred my ſelf of that order, and to haue taken on their threefold vow, the third whereof, which is of a blind &amp; abſolute obedience to the ſuperiors of that order, renun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing both my will and iudgment (as their Father <hi>Ignatius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">His Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to his Brethren in <hi>Luſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tania.</hi>
                  </note> calls it) and to follow al their injunctions without asking queſtion to goe, or to ſtay, to do or to ſuffer whatſoeuer they thought good to enjoyne mee for the Catholick cauſe and good of the Roman Church, This oath J ſaye <hi>I</hi> could not get digeſted. For therby J ſhould haue bene bound, if they had thought it fit to enjoyne mee for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17649:10"/> the advancement of the Catholick cauſe, to haue beene an inſtrument of all the miſchiefe that they could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe againſt my natiue Countrie, and vnder colour of re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lieving ſoules to doe what any hath done or attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that blind obedience. Skarring therefore at this oath, I came home, and yet forced my ſelf ſtill to keep the former grounds of Religion: whereby I was made obſtinat in errour, and vntoward to be dealt with by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who wold haue ſtudied to reclaime me: Yet it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God at laſt to force in his own truth vpon my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that I began to ſmell ſundrie of their errours, and ſpecially of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe and tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, that I began to examine theſe groundes of the Roman Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I had drunk in the beginning if they could beare me out before God or not: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in finding my ſelfe miſerablie miſtaken, and ſo long by that meanes abuſed, freelie and of my own accord, not beeing dealt with by any, J addreſſed my ſelfe for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with the Miniſterie of <hi>Edinburgh, Falkirke</hi> and <hi>Glaſgow:</hi> who all louingly and learnedly gaue mee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to all my doubts, and furthered this worke of God in helping home a forlorne Sonne to his Fathers houſe againe.</p>
               <p>Now for all the particular reaſons why I call their maſſe and tranſubſtantiation an errour, and the grounds of their Religion vnwarandable, and why J haue renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their particular errours builded thereon, it were not convenient to ſet them all down here: partly becauſe it wold accreſſe to a volume, partly becauſe in ſubſtance they are the ſame that are learnedlie ſet down by theſe who handles the contrauerſies againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Only J will content my ſelfe to ſhew ſome few
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17649:10"/> things of many. Firſt, concerning their Religion in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. Next, concerning their maſſe, adding therto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly in the third place, ſome few things of their common abſurdities maintained by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Scriptures alledged imperfection, &amp; the Pope of <hi>Romes</hi> perfection, who can not erre as is alledged, becauſe hee ſits in the Chaire of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> are the two rotten Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, whereon all theſe errours are builded.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Romiſh Religion is a myſterie: it makes ſhow to hold the common groundes of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie, but by her deedes everts them. The firſt principles of the Romiſh errours doe reſolue vpon theſe two, the imperfection of the Scripture, and the peereleſſe prerogatiue of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> As for the imperfection of the Scripture, they alledge that it does not containe all things neceſſarie for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but place muſt bee left for traditions, that is, vnwriten doctrinall poynts, and ancient cuſtomes long vſed in the Church, as alſo for Eccleſiaſticall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and determinations or definitive ſentences in matters controverted: all which they alledge muſt haue equall authoritie in mens mindes with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>Next, they alledge that theſe points neceſſarie to Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which are ſet down in Scripture are not cleare and plaine in the Scripture, but that the Scripture is obſcure and doubtſome, and therefore is neither neceſſarie nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17649:11"/> expedient that it ſhould bee tranſlated, that it is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing for laicks to read it: wherein, to any that will looke narrowlie vpon the matter, they bewray a ſecreet feare, if they bee hemde in into the rule of the Scriptures, they cannot iuſtifie with any colour the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of their errours.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, evidently they ſhow that the reading of the Scriptures by laicks ſhuld breed moe doubts about their Religion than they could bee able to ſolve, and giue them ſuch inſight in this Religion, that theſe whom they keepe now in the chaines of darkneſſe and blinde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe cauſing them to doe, and ſuffer and beleeue what they pleaſe, could not but break the yock if they grew acquainted with the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Fourthlie, they bewray the Spirit of Antichriſt, who thus vnder faire pretences ſclander Chriſt Jeſus. who hauing taken vpon him, as the great Prophet and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of his Church, to reveale the whole Counſell of God concerning mens Saluation, and cauſed ſet it downe in Scripture, yet hath come ſhort of his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as their doctrine importes, and neither hath ſet downe all things needfull, nor theſe clearly which are ſet downe, but obſcurely, ambiguouſly and dangerou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, that it is not ſafe for common People to read the ſame: and ſo by theſe meanes they breed a miſregard of the Scripture of Chriſt in mens hearts, and skarres Chriſts ſheepe as long as they can from hearing what the Spirit of Chriſt ſayeth to his Churches.</p>
               <p>As for the peereleſſe prerogatiue of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the firſt is, that ſhe cannot erre. If wee aske how this can bee, ſince they cannot name ſix men liuing of the Romiſh Religion, of whom they either dare or wil avow
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17649:11"/> but they may erre, and are ſubject thereto, nor three, nor two. They will anſwere, that yet there is one who is head of all the reſt of that Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Pope, who cannot erre, all the reſt of the Church-men of that profeſſion being gathered together without him, or without his minde, ſent by his Legat or Nuncio to them, they grant they may erre, only he cannot erre. So then in ſtead of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we haue the Pope, whoſe councill of Cardinals they will ioyne with him for luſters cauſe: but the infallibilitie of doctrine they place in none but the Pope only. By vertue of this prerogatiue of the Pope they aſcribe great things to the Church of Rome, vnder this pretence all her traditions are Apoſtolicke, albeit they bee not in Scripture, becauſe they are come down, as is alledged; through the Apoſtolicke channell of the Popes infallibilitie. Vnder this pretence all her cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and obſeruations are Catholicke and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and all her Eccleſiaſticke conſtitutions, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive ſentences in matters contraverted are of diuine authoritie as they alledge, and doe oblige men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe &amp; obedience no leſſe than the Scripture. Yea, vnder this pretence the Scripture hath no authoritie in reſpect of theſe who beleeue it, wherfore it ſhuld perſuade them or be credited more than the fables of <hi>Eſope,</hi> but as much as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> allowes vpon it. Vnder this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, when other Churches doechallenge the Roman Church for any fault or errour, ſhee takes vpon her to bee judge in all controuerſies betwixt her ſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The Greeke Church for example in <hi>Aſia</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges her of vſurpation aboue other Churches; ſhee will be iudge, challenges her of defection from Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicke doctrine, ſhee will bee iudge: challenges her
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17649:12"/> of not doing as ſhee ought to doe, or Chriſts ſpouſe ought to do, ſhee will be iudge: yea, ſhee will giue the ſenſe of the Scripture and the expoſition of it as ſhal beſt ſerue to iuſtifie her owne cauſe: and if any man ſhall take a ſentence of Scripture otherwiſe than ſhee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes them, than that ſentence ſo taken ſhall not bee accounted Scripture. Theſe and other ſuch like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences they draw and deduce from this one foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can not erre. Aske a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of them, why cannot your Pope erre, ſeeing he is a ſinfull man as well as others, as they will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and they leaſt of all who are beſt acquaint with the Popes priuate conuerſation, ſeeing it is poſſible that the Cardinalls (who are ſubiect to errour, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when their head is dead, and a new Pope not yet created) ſeeing they may erre in chooſing an vnfit man for ſo great a charge, what warrand can they ſhow to giue aſſurance that ſuch a Pope cannot erre. They anſwere at laſt, albeit they ſhift poſſibliea while, becaus Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was head of the whole Catholick Church in his time hauing ſupreme authoritie and the fulneſſe of paſtorall power in doctrine and gouernment ouer the reſt of the Apoſtles, and all the Churches of the Worlde. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſo qualified ſay they, was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and there is his Chaire, and the Popes are his only lawfull ſucceſſours, inueſted lawfully by God in the ſame Apoſtolicke authoritie, ouer all the ſheepe of Chriſt, and all that may bee ſheepe in the World, and is as infalliblie aſſiſted by the holy Spirit as euer the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was, after the deſcending of the holy Ghoſt vpon him, in the Pentecoſt. This is the key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of their whole building: this is the Pillar of whole
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17649:12"/> Popedome: if this ſtand, the better for them: if this fall, all goes to the ground, and all that is builded thereon: for if either they faile in prouing Saint Peters ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, or his Romiſh Epiſcopacie, or the Popes lawfullſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in Apoſtolick authoritie, and other priuiledges, then the Popes infallibilitie, and the Roman Churches certaintie, with all their traditions, cuſtomes, conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and all the reſt of that worke of theirs builded thereon ſhall hurle to the ground together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>No Papiſt in the Earth can ſhew one cleare teſtimonie of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make good that ever Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was at Rome, or Biſhop of Rome, or that the Pope is his ſpeciall ſucceſſour in his Apoſtolicke office.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O examine then theſe grounds, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome taſte may be giuen briefly of that Cup, which <hi>Rome</hi> propynes to the World, and the Princes therof to drinke, that they may fall in loue with her; J will ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the Apoſtolicke authoritie of the Lords deare ſervant Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> nor to his perſonall prerogatiue in age, in time of following Chriſt, in zeale and painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in his calling: Yet let me vindicate him a litle from that iniurie which his pretended ſucceſſours doe him: who father the baſphemous titles of their Antichriſtian vſurpation and tyrannie ouer Gods Church vpon him. For this peereleſſe power above the whole Apoſtles, &amp; headſhip of the Church which they alledge is a thing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17649:13"/> which without blaſphemie cannot bee aſcribed to any mortall man: becauſe Chriſt in his holy Scripture claims this for his owne royall prerogatiue to bee head of his Church, and to haue the Church his body and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; To bee the husband of his Church, and to haue the Church his ſpouſe, and not anothers: for theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Sauiour of the Church, who is Chriſt only, and not another, and therefore theſe three ſtyles are<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 23.</note> joyned together and aſcribed to him. And this ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of <hi>Peter</hi> ouer the Apoſtles is a forgerie only of theſe who would haue ſome ſcugge for their vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">Math. 28. 19. Matth. 23. 8. 9. Marke 9. 33 34. Luk. 22. 26. 1. Pet. 5. 3. 4.</note> for Chriſt gaue all his Apoſtles equall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, equalled them as brethren, and diſcharged any of them to take any maioririe or ſupremacie one ouer another: And when in their infirmitie they ſtrove for it Chriſt rebuked them: and the night before hee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered diſcharged the ſame abſolutly among them. Next <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe diſclaimes this ſupremacie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it only to Ieſus Chriſt, and diſcharges all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Lordſhip ouer the Lords inheritance. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies the trueth of this, for magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his Apoſtleſhip, he avows he was nothing inferior<note place="margin">2 Corin. 11. 5. Gal. 1. 1. 16. 17. 18. 1. Cor. 3. 21. 22.</note> to the chiefeſt Apoſtles: And declares that hee recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his Apoſtleſhip from Chriſt immediatlie, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed it ſundrie yeares before he ſaw <hi>Peter:</hi> and diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth all to glorie in men, whether <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> that is, <hi>Peter,</hi> or <hi>Apollos</hi> or any other. But becauſe this is not the maine matter, let vs come to that wherevpon all ſtands. How proue they that <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome</hi> or Biſhop there? or that God hath tied his Spirit to who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhould bee Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> after him. So weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a matter as the Popes ſtanding or falling, ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17649:13"/> maine an Article of Roman Catholick Faith, the only Pillar of the Romiſh Religion, the ground of the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo many ſinnes, of ſauing or damning ſo many Soules, hath neede of expreſſe, direct and ample war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand from the divine Scripture; or elſe of need force the weight of Roman Religion is builded upon the ſand, and hath no warrand from God, Let them but ſhow vs one teſtimonie out of all the holy Scripture that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was properly Biſhop of <hi>Rome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and next let them ſhow any teſtimonie out of the ſame Scripture, that the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> are priuiledged from erring, more than other men, and are indued with as infallible aſſiſtance of the holy Spirit as <hi>Peter.</hi> They will produce to vs their owne flatterers and old ſtorie writers, who both in thoſe maters and others diſagree among themſelves. But who are theſe that the Soules of ſo many thouſands ſhould bee grounded vpon their worde? to ſpeake nothing of the fables that is found in them, and of the ſmall reſpect that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> carries to them, when they ſeeme to make any thing againſt them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay againe, let them produce divine warrand out of the Scripture, or els let me be iuſtified, who after the tryall of their falſhood and deceat, haue departed from them as ſeducers, who when J followed their grounds to the vttermoſt, could giue mee no warrand, for the grounds whereon all their Religion ſtands, but ſuch as are taken from behind the Bible from lying mens words and forged hiſtories, ſuppoſititous treatiſes of the fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; helpers vp of their monſtruous head the Pope, aboue the Church: either let them proue theſe prime Pillars of their Religion, or elſe let all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes who in their heart would faine bee at Chriſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17649:14"/> forſake their ſeducers as J haue done vpon iuſt grounds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But becaus it is impoſſible for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to proue S. <hi>Peter</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> from Scripture, far leſſe that all the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> ſince the Apoſtles time were as infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie aſſiſted with the holy Spirit and ſet vp in the ſame Apoſtolick authoritie that he had, J will ſay ſomething againſt theſe for ſuch as faine would know the right, to thinke vpon, till they proue the ſame groundes out of Scripture. The Scripture giues great probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that <hi>Peter</hi> was not in <hi>Rome</hi> at all, farre leſſe to fixe his Epiſcopall Chaire there: For firſt, before <hi>Paul</hi> did write to the Romans, <hi>Peter</hi> was not at <hi>Rome</hi> far leſſe Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> for then <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould haue made ſome mention of him, confirmed his doctrine, commended his labour, and ſaluted him among the firſt, but this he doth not. Secondly, Chriſtianitie would not haue beene ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth to the Iewes at <hi>Rome</hi> who deſired to heare of it by<note place="margin">Act 28 22. 2 Tim. 4 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> as a noueltie, if <hi>Peter</hi> had beene there before <hi>Paul</hi> came to bee priſoner. Thirdlie, when <hi>Paul</hi> was arraigned before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> all forſooke him. Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> was not there: except they will lay a ſecond deniall of Chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Jn all his Epiſtles written when hee was priſoner at <hi>Rome,</hi> he tels who were his helpers, among whom <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is neuer mentioned. Laſt of all it is writen how <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 7. 8. 9.</note> preached among the circumciſion and proſpered in the Goſpell, and <hi>Paul</hi> preached among the Gentiles and proſpered. Then how <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers made a couenant that <hi>Paule</hi> ſhould preach to the Gentiles, and <hi>Peter</hi> to the circumciſion, that is, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould exerciſe his Apoſtolicke office, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially among the Gentiles, and <hi>Peter</hi> his among the Jewes. From hence I reaſon, if <hi>Peter</hi> had either beene,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17649:14"/> or purpoſed to haue beene Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> hee would not haue made that paction, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould preach to the Gentiles, of whom, the Romanes were a part, and taken himſelf to the Jewes for his lot. But that hee did make this Paction or couenant is euident out of the place cited: therefore neither was <hi>Peter</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor purpoſed to bee Biſhop of it: if they ſay hee was Biſhop before this Couenant, then he forſooke his Biſhopricke; if they ſay after, then hee broke his Couenant, and changed his minde, and did contrare to his purpoſe. He that conſiders the nature of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip, &amp; of a Biſhoprick properly taken, will ſee that this ground of theirs is a fiction, for to make an Apoſtle proper Biſhop of any Town, is to digraduate him from his Apoſtolick office, as far, as to make the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> Pariſh-prieſt in a landward Village. Laſtly it wants not a myſterie that they can not make out the ſuppu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of theſe yeeres which their common opinion aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes to <hi>Peters</hi> biſhoping at <hi>Rome:</hi> as likewiſe they can not reconcile the different opinions anent <hi>Peters</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat ſucceſſors whether it was <hi>Linus, Clemens,</hi> or <hi>Cletus:</hi> A wonder it is that the faſtening of the body of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſhuld be ſo vncertaine: but the truth is, that God heereby would declare to theſe who are not blinded, that the miſterie of iniquitie lurketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe, and the like miſts: This for <hi>Peters</hi> not beeing at <hi>Rome.</hi> Now that the Pope is not lawfull ſucceſſour to <hi>Peter</hi> in his Apoſtolicke office, J cleare it thus, he hath neither Apoſtolicke office, nor Apoſtolicke qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification, nor Apoſtolicke calling and entrie to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice hee pretends. Therefore hee cannot bee either lawfull ſucceſſour to <hi>Peter</hi> or any of the Apoſtles in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17649:15"/> that Apoſtolicke charge. The office of <hi>Peter</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Apoſtles, was, to goe and teach, and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize all Nations; that is, in their owne proper perſon, to goe from place to place, by preaching to plant Churches and to eſtabliſh them. But the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> ſtayes in their palaces, and neither teaches, nor baptizes. Therefore in their office they are not their ſucceſſours. Secondlie, <hi>Peter</hi> and others Apoſtles were immediatly called, and entered into their office by Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe: but the Popes are choſen by their owne Creaturs, the Cardinals, who neither haue their owne office of God, nor power of God to giue ſuch office to the Pope. Thirdly, <hi>Peter</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles were authoriſed to write canonicall Scripture, and were indued with the gift of miracles, God teſtifieing to the World his extraordinar Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion giuen to them: ſo are not the Popes qualified: therefore they are not <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſours. Thus I haue ſhowne that one of the two greateſt pillars of Poperie ſtands vpon the ſand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That this rotten and falling pillar of the Popes ſupremacie may bee maintained, they leaue no humane policie vn-at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He veritie of this, firſt is cleare by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of their Popes and Cardinalls, who for the moſt parte are of noble birth in this Worlde, the ſecond or third ſonnes of Princes, and great men in <hi>Italie, Spaine, Germanie</hi> and other partes where the Romiſh Religion hath place, by whoſe Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, friendſhip and Allyance, the Pope and Popedome
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17649:15"/> is ſtrengthned in al places. Next for every Nation, among the reſt for <hi>Scotland, England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> there are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Cardinals protectors, as they call them, at <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; men who haue Church offices &amp; honor at <hi>Rome</hi> to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure &amp; draw in by all their moyen whom they can; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſuch as out of curioſity in traueling do reſort thither; &amp; lands &amp; rents in &amp; about <hi>Rome,</hi> beſides their purchaſe, which is, often more than their ſet Rent, are not deficient. Then there are Cardinals ſent forth from the court of <hi>Rome</hi> into all Cuntries where Popedome hath place, to ſee to the ſtanding of the Popes grandour, &amp; that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be giuen to his Holineſſe, as they ſay, euerywhere. Under them in euerie Cuntrie where Romiſh Religion hath place, are Primates, Abbots, Metropolitanes, Suffraganes, with many other their attendans, &amp;c. vnto whom euerie-where large Rents of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living, and caſualities and commodities doe appertaine, all theſe by their whole ſtrength, ſtudie to vphold the Popes grandure. Vnder theſe againe are exceeding many ordouts of Monkes, of Friers of diverſe colours or habits, <hi>Dominicanes</hi> or <hi>Iacobines, Auguſtines, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictines, Franciſcans, Capucians, Gray Friers, Recollects, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſians, Carms, Minims,</hi> and <hi>Ieſuits</hi> &amp;c. hudge num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of all theſe of whom ſome liue by ſet Rents, ſome goe a begging, ſome liue on their purchaſe as they beſt may all theſe beſide their proper motiues to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Sea of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſolemnly ſworne to that effect, that they ſhall maintaine, defend and doe their vttermoſt for the honour welfare and grandour, of their holy Father the Pope. Beſides theſe they haue all the common people tied vnto them by bands, not laid vpon their bodies, but vpon their Soules, by
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17649:16"/> their doctrine of auriculare confeſſion, whereby vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of not beeing forgiuen their ſinnes, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall condemnation, they make them reveale not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their ſecreet actuall turpitude (wherevpon what abuſe followes J neede not inſiſt) but alſo their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes and intentions which they haue had to ſinne, and in ſpeciall if they bee priuie to any thing againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> their holy mother; by which means they not only bring peoples mindes in a ſeruile ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to themſelues (for none can haue more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement ouer one than their Father confeſſour) but alſo by their intelligencing this way, make the Pope their Monarch dreadfull to all Kings of the Earth, for he will doe more by a ſyde Cloake and a ſharp knife in one houre, than the mightieſt Prince in the Earth will doe by fourtie thouſand armed men in a long time: yet hee ſhould doe leſſe harme if hee were leſſe dred: for when men are more feared to grieue the Pope than God, what wonder the Lord let him bee a ſcourge to them? This their ſtrong ſort of Gouernement, (more wittilie deuiſed than euer the old Senate diſpoſed the ruling of the conquered Prouinces, or conquering of new) they ſecond with the extreame ſhow and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall luſter of holineſſe and Religion. For the multitude of Religious Orders, with houſes and Cloſters and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in them, with the pretenſe of their ſingle and chaſt life, the multitude of Religious exerciſes, Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke houres, faſtes, Feaſtes, holy dayes, the multitude of Altars, Jmages, and rich Ornaments of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the multitude of all ſort of Ceremonies, that may carry appearance of Diuinitie. The multitude of poore people enduring pennance, going in Pilgrimage, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17649:16"/> wonderfull mercileſneſſe of poore tormented conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſcourging themſelues openlie in their ſtreetes with their faces couered, at the direction ſometimes of their confeſſour, ſometimes voluntarlie, ſuppoſing this way to doe away their ſinnes, and pacifie Gods wrath, and their owne perplexed conſcience, together with the profeſſion of the common grounds of Chriſtianitie, which Papiſts makes ſhow of, ſo aſtoniſhes the mindes of the ſimple people, ſo rauiſhes and amazes ignorant on-lookers, ſo inchants and ſo bewitches the multitude, that they cannot thinke but God will be as well pleaſed with ſuch follies, as they are themſelves, not knowing what is pleaſant to him by his own Word, or that will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, though neuer ſo ſpecious, is abominable to him. Then to back and beamfill all, comes in their ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Prieſts, and preaching Friers, and the late ordour of the Jeſuits, by all their powerfull perſuaſion to preſſe the receauing of the grounds of Roman Religion vpon men, and by a ſhew of Philoſophy, and the Wiſedome of this Worlde that comes to nought, and the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of ſcience falſly ſo called, (the inſtruments whereby Sathan oppoſed the Apoſtles of old) they ſtriue to make all ſeeme good that the Roman Church doeth, and that all is euill that they doe not. But where ſhall all the riches bee gotten to vphold ſuch a ſtatelie Monarchie as this, and ſo many ſeruants of that ſtate? for anſwere, they haue ſo many points of gain full doctrine, as firſt of the merit of good works, &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erogation of the merites of Saints, which furniſheth the treaſure of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> among which goode workes, eſpeciallie Almes, this muſt be held for a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that thoſe who haue wealth cannot doe a more
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17649:17"/> meritorious worke to purchaſe heauen by, than by largelie beſtowing vpon religious men and their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance. Secondly the Doctrine of pennance and of indulgence, and ſatiſfaction; which ſometime rendred the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> a great deale more than now it doeth, and yet brings hudge moneyes to that Sea. Thirdly, the doctrine of purgatorie nothing inferiour to any of the former: for theſe who could not be enduced to giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing largely in the time of their life, at the time of their death for feare of Purgatory, to the end that they may win out of Purgatorie fire ſoone, by the vertue of Soul maſſes, &amp; religious mens devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, will be willing to mortify or leaue in Legacie what their Fatherconfeſſor thinks expedient, and that of the readieſt. Fourthlie, the ſtraite vrging the thre-fold vow of ſingle life, povertie, Canonicall obedience, vpon all them whom they can perſuade to rander themſelfe religious. For by this meanes the ſeuerall Religious ordours, but eſpecially the Jeſuites, if they can by any meanes perſuade a man of wealth, or a rich burges heire, a Noble mans ſon, or an heritour of Lands, (as they perſuade too too many to bee of their ordours,) then hee renounces all his means to bee diſpoſed vpon, by the ſuperiour of the ordour; and hee himſelfe with the reſt profeſſes pouertie, and liues vpon the common Purſe, or his purchaſe if hee be ſent out or imployed in ſeruice. Theſe, and many moe means vnſearchable, they haue of drawing in Rents &amp; moyons to themſelf, beſide offrings to Altars, extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary maſſe. Caſualitie at burials, and ſuch lik. In al which things and ſindrie other poynts both of practiſe and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, they will bee ſparing in any part, where they are ſeeking to make conqueſt, as in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17649:17"/> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> for feare to loſe their prey; but when and where they are ſettled any man that trauells, if he pleaſe may try the trueth, whether it bee not as J ſay and more: for I will bee ſparing to ſpeake all, leſt I ſhould ſee me to taxe particular perſons, rather than to ſeeke the furtherance of the true and diſgrace of counterfeit Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That the Scriptures imperfection and obſcuritie is wrongfully alledged by Papiſts.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus hauing at length diſcouered the main pillar of Popedome with ſome of their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane policies for vpholding the ſame, I wil ſpeake ſhortly a worde or two againſt the imperfection &amp; obſcuritie which they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Scripture. This ſaying is ſo blaſphen ous againſt God the author of the Scripture, Let the Lord<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15. 16. 17. Ioh 5. 39.</note> anſwere for himſelf. By his Apoſtle <hi>All Scripture is giuen by diuine inſpiration &amp;c. That the man of God may be made perfect throughly furniſhed vnto all good works.</hi> And by his ſonne <hi>who hath giuen Commandement to thoſe who thinks to haue eternall life to ſearch the Scriptures.</hi> Jf thou will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey this command, conſtantly praying to God for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge dayly: the Lord ſhall ſhow thee in reading of it that they are his enemies who haue ſo diſgraced his writings. wherefore I would perſuade young Schollers, and others of young yeeres, to drink in the knowledge of the Scriptures and neuer to quite the light thereof,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17649:18"/> which the Lord hath appointed to direct vs. <hi>Wee haue alſo a more ſure Word of Propheſie, whereunto yee doe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, Pet. 1. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>well that yee take heede as vnto a light that ſhineth in a dark place. &amp;c.</hi> Next when doubts of Religion are caſten in their minde, the not running to God by Prayer, as the fountaine of Religion, and to ſuch Godly and truelie learned men, who are content that all they ſay, bee examined according to the Scripture, is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſe of provocation of God, to giue them ouer to belieue lyes, who thus deſpyſing the right meanes, and loue of the trueth, <hi>will not goe to law and teſtimonies.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 8. 20, 1. Tim. 4. 1. Rom. 1. 21.</note> as God directeth them. <hi>But giues eare to ſeducing Spirites, and doctrine of Deuills,</hi> as the Apoſtle calles them. Further, <hi>when men knowes God, and glorifies him not as God, they become vaine in their owne ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and their fooliſh hearts are darkened in Gods iuſtice,</hi> as is ſaid of the Gentiles. If thou will not obey this forſaid command and counſell, it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to diſpute this queſtion further before thee, as to diſpute what taſte the honey or the honey combe hath with them, that neuer taſted thereof, for feare it poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon them. And this much for the firſt part, I promiſed to ſpeake, which was of their Religion in generall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>No certaintie to haue the true Chriſt, or to bee free from Idolatrie of a falſe Chriſt in the Maſſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ollowes heare the next poynt, whereof J pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to ſpeake, to wit, of the Maſſe: but I ſhall
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17649:18"/> ſhall inſiſt moſt vpon that groſſe here ſie of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. For vpholding wherof their ſpecial ground is the words of the inſtitution; <hi>This is my bodie:</hi> which neuer can inforce tranſubſtantiation, for firſt Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine in his third booke of the Euchariſt, <hi>Secundo dicit</hi>
                  <note place="margin">chap. 23</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Declares that <hi>Scotus</hi> ſayes, there is no place of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſo plaine, that compelles euidently to admit tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantitaion, without the declaration of the Church. And Bellarmine himſelfe acknowledges, that not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to bee improbable. Next, they aggrie not them ſelues vpon the expoſition of theſe words, ſo that they cannot condeſcend vpon the verie firſt word <hi>HOC, this,</hi> as Bellarmine acknowledges of the Euchariſt. Where refuſing the opinion of other Catholicks, hee takes him to this interpretation that <hi>HOC, This,</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>ſub his ſpeciebus contentum, contained vnder theſe ſpeces,</hi> which indeed is an vncouth acception of the worde, ſuch as is not to bee found in any author either diuine or hu mane; and yet it makes nothing to the purpoſe: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it may euer bee demanded, what is that which is <hi>Sub his ſpeciebus, vnder theſe ſpeces:</hi> for that muſt bee either the bread, or the bodie of Chriſt: if they vnderſtand the bodie of Chriſt, then, the meaning in their expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, the bodie of Chriſt is the bodie of Chriſt; Which neither agries with Chriſts purpoſe, nor yet proues their purpoſe, for the body of Chriſt may bee the body of Chriſt, and yet no change made of the bread in the ſubſtance of Chriſts bodie. And by, <hi>This,</hi> if they vnderſtand bread, then the force of the words will bee, <hi>This breadis Chriſts bodie:</hi> But neither will this proue their purpoſe, becauſe it is not ſaide, the ſubſtance of this Bread, is changed in the ſubſtance of Chriſtes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17649:19"/> body, as they expone it, But only <hi>This is my body,</hi> which no more can inferre the change of ſubſtance in ſubſtance, then theſe wordes which hee ſaide <hi>I am the true vyne,</hi> can inferre a ſubſtantiall change of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">Ioh. 15. 1. 5. 1. Cor. 11. 25.</note> in a vine tree, or theſe words, which hee ſaid in the ſame Supper, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſhowes, <hi>This cup is the new Teſtament,</hi> can enforce either the change of the ſubſtance of the cup, or of the vine in the cup in a Teſtament. So I could finde no warrand out of Chriſts words for tranſubſtantiation, J might well take their worde for it in ſtead of Chriſts.</p>
               <p>Next, their doctrine could giue mee no infallible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie that I ſhould bee free from worſhiping an J doll, and the fantaſie of my owne braine in ſtead of Chriſt, when J came to the Maſſe: for their doctrine is, except the Prieſt haue a ſpeciall intention to conſecrate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit hee ſay Maſſe, that no tranſubſtantiation will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and ſo all that are preſent at the Maſſe, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, as they grant. Now what can any man haue but a probable conjecture or charitable opinion, or ſtrong apprehenſion of another mans intention, infallible cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie can he not haue: And I in ſpeciall, who knew certainly ſome of theſe Prieſts who were choſen, and ſent out by their ſuperiours to propagate the Romiſh Religion, ſubiect to as groſſe faultes in their life, for drunkenneſſe, and ſundrie other vices, as other ſinfull Laicks, as they call them: and yet part of them ſaid Maſſe many a time, both neere hand, and further off: how could I then but be ſuſpenſe about their intention, and how could J but doubt whether God would bee pleaſed at ſuch mens intentions to change bread in Chriſts body, and to put Chriſt in their hands, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17649:19"/> mouthes, and to allow them to bee Prieſts, to offer the Sonne of God his body in a ſacrifice to the Father. J know what they vſe to anſwere in ſuch caſes, that the Peoples worſhipping of a ſuppoſed tranſubſtantiat ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie were but materiall Jdolatrie, becauſe their purpoſe was to worſhip the true Chriſt, when they worſhiped only bread, and the Idoll of their owne imagination. But alace, this is a poore ſhift, and no better than if one ſhould comfort a woman who had lyen with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſides her husband, ſaying to her, no matter this adulterie of thine is but materiall only, and not formall; becauſe thy purpoſe was to giue thy body to thy hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and no other. For the Scripture compares Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie<note place="margin">Ieremie 3. 1. 2.</note> and adulterie together verie often.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I found their tranſubſtantiation builded vpon a pretenſe of making men certaine of their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and coniunction with Chriſt: which coniunction if it may bee ſure without a corporall preſence of his body, their tranſubſtantiation is a needleſſe fiction.</p>
               <p>Now I vnderſtand certainly that, howſoeuer the Papiſts doe traduce Miniſters, as if they fed people with ſignes and ſhadowes, yet they belieue and teach, that they are made ſure of Ieſus our Lord. Firſt by his couenant and promiſe, as theſe that are eſpouſed, beeing faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full one to another, are made ſure one of another before their compleet marriage, by mutuall affection of heart, conſent and couenant, and mutuall promiſe: for which cauſe, the ſpouſe in the Canticles many a yeere before Chriſts incarnation, ſaid, <hi>My beloued is mine, and I am</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 2. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>his.</hi> Next they belieue and teach that they are made ſure of Chriſt, by his owne great Seales annexed to his couenant, the two Sacraments, Baptiſme, and the Lords
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17649:20"/> Supper, which the Lord hath ordained to be the pawns, pledges and Seales of himſelf his gifts, and his graces beſtowed vpon them, and ſo are made ſure of Chriſt, and his grace for their Saluation, as men are made ſure of the Kings gift when they haue his royall donation, and his great Seales annexed thereto: for which cauſe, When our Lord had giuen the Sacramentes to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, he ſayes, J diſpone or appoynt a Kingdome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Luk. 22. 9,</note> you; becauſe hee had giuen them the Seales of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereof preſently before. Thirdly, they teach that they are made ſure of Chriſt, by the Spirite of Chriſt, whom Chriſt promiſes, and giues to euerie one that beleeues in him, in ſuch ſort that hee who hath not<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 9</note> the Spirite of Chriſt is none of his. By which Spirite Chriſt is joyned to them, and they to Chriſt, as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one body are ioyned to the head, and quickned by one Spirite: for which cauſe of Chriſt it is ſaid that he dwels in vs, and wee in him, he is the head, and wee<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3. 17, 4. 16</note> are the members of his myſticall bodie. By this three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold certaintie they teach and belieue that they are made ſure of Chriſt in the Sacrament, for performance wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſhow that there is no neceſſitie of corporall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Firſt, becauſe theſe meanes of certaintie were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted of Chriſt to ſupplee his corporall abſence till his ſecond comming againe. Secondly, becauſe the Sonne of God is more able after this manner from Heauen to communicate himſelfe to vs on Earth then the Sun that ſhines dayly is able from Heauen to giue light and heate to vs on Earth, without deſcending cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally to vs. Then for the expoſition of the wordes of the Sacrament <hi>This is my body,</hi> they profeſſe to expone them as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expones them, who ſayes, that the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17649:20"/> bread which we break is the communion of the body of<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10 16. 1 Cor. 11 25.</note> Ieſus, the cup which wee bleſſe is the Communion of the blood of Chriſt, and as Chriſt ſpeaking of the cup it muſt be exponed: <hi>This cup is the new Teſtament or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in my blood,</hi> and according to the vſuall forme of the Scripture language concerning Sacraments, where the name of the gift is giuen to the Seale to aſſure them who faithully receaue the one, that they are made ſure of the other; or the name of a mercie beſtowed is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the memoriall of it, to make the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that mercy more freſh and liuelie. Seeing that therefore J could find for the Romiſh doctrine of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation no warrand of the Lords worde, and by that doctrine, no ground of infallible certaintie to free mee from Idolatrie; but on the contrare grounds of aſſurance, that it could not bee that God would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Sonne any more to perſonall ſuffering of ſuch indignities as is done him in the Maſſe; Let any man iudge whether I had reaſon to ſute to bee receaued to the communion with him, according to the warrand of his owne worde, and bee free for euer from all perill of that groſſe Idolatrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Maſſe drawes away from Chriſts rule of the Sacrament and defaces his inſtitution.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He next reaſon why J call the Maſſe an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, is becauſe it doth leade men away from the right rule of the Sacrament to follow mens deuices, and forged myſticall rites of mens appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17649:21"/> whereof the Lord hath pronounced in generall: <hi>In vaine doe they worſhip mee, teaching for doctrine the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of men:</hi> Which howſoeuer they bee in eſtimation among men, yet are abominable before God: for our Lord Jeſus, beeing to leaue the World in regarde of his corporall preſence, thought good to appoynt a holy Supper wherein hee will haue his bodilie ſufferings, and bloodſhed and death repreſented and brought to freſh remembrance by the breaking of bread and wine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out in a cup; and the Soules of his faithfull ones fed &amp; comforted in the aſſurance that his body was broken for them, and his blood ſhed for the remiſſion of their ſinnes, by eating of the bread broken, and drinking of the wine powred in the cup; which eating and drinking ſhould bee to them a pledge and ſeale of their ſpirituall coniunction with CHRIST, and partaking of his life as certainely wrought by his ſpirit, as if theſe ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which they did eate and drinke were ioyned with their bodies. Then which ordinance of our Lord no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can bee more ſweet to a Soule that conſiders his purpoſe therein: and therefore he hath commanded not his Miniſters only, but his whole Church on Earth to doe this in remembrance of him following his example as he hath cauſed ſet down by his pen-men in his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee followed till his ſecond comming againe. But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as her defection hath growne peece and peece, hath ſo far departed from the rule, that ſcarſly now in their Maſſe can the footſteps of Chriſts ordinance be ſeene: for vnder pretenſe that they are not tied to follow theſe circumſtances which were proper to the firſt Supper, ſuch as are the time, after Supper; the place, an vpper Chamber; the number of perſons,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17649:21"/> eleuen or twelue; the ſexe, men only and not women: which any man may perceiue to bee proper to that firſt time, and not belonging to the nature of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: if theſe circumſtances were vrged vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally they ſhould marre and hinder that action, and the comfort of the communicants, women beeing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, the night taking when the day was free, a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber taking wherein all the Church could not aſſemble, and twelue only admitted, where fourtie twelues were prepared and waiting on: vnder pretenſe, I ſay, of not beeing tied to theſe foure circumſtances, when they may be prejudiciall to the action, they haue taken liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to alter the ſubſtance, and ſacramentall rites of this Supper left to be imitate by all Chriſts Churches till his ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming again: for as thogh Chriſts ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce had beene too baſe and ſimple, they haue deuiſed to cloath their Prieſts in brodering of ſilk and ſiluer and gold, and to make ſumptuous Maſſe cloathes to ſet out their work with all: As if Chriſt his ceremonies had beene of ſmall ſignification, they haue caſten them by, and appoynted new ones of their owne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> making myſticall ſignifications of their owne deuiſing, As if the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluouſly from Chriſts mouth giuen commandement to the common people to drink of the cup, they haue cutte off the halfe of the peoples comfort, and witholden the cup from them: As if the Lord had not done wiſely in vſing plaine language to his diſciples, ſuch as they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, they haue rolled vp all in an vncouth language commanding that Maſſe ſhould only bee ſaid in Latine: As if our Lord had not well conſidered, what belongs to the holyneſſe of ſuch a worke, in taking ſuch bread as was vſuall in the Land, and as the Maſter of the houſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17649:22"/> laid downe before him to Supper, they haue made a round Maſſe bread, the quantitie of twelvepence, or ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, and as thin as they can cauſe it ſticke together, with a ſtamped crucifixe on the one ſide of it for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they haue turned the communion of a number, to the Prieſts drinking and eating alone, the Lords table to a ſtone Altar, the memoriall of his death to an imaginary corporall preſence; the ſeale of Gods giuing of Chriſt vnto men, into mens offering vp of Chriſt to God, Gods Sacrament, into mans ſacrificing of the ſonne of God to the Father; in a worde they haue turned Chriſts holy Supper in the Popes Maſſe, and ſo, what by adding, what by pairing, what by altering and chopping and changing they haue mutilated deformed and defaced Gods ordinance, falſified King Jeſus his great ſeale and corrupted his teſtament, that he who is partaker of the Maſſe, thinking to get Gods bleſſing by it, caſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in danger of Gods curſe, for beeing guiltie of ſo manifold diſhonoring of the ſonne of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Maſſe drawes men from the true Chriſt, to adore and belieue in a falſe Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third reaſon why J call the Maſſe, and their pretended tranſubſtantiation in it an errour, is this. Becauſe it hath drawne mee and doth drawe all that beleeues it, from the true Chriſt Jeſus deſcribed in the holy Scripture to a falſe Chriſt forged in their fantaſie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17649:22"/> and braines of men, giuen ouer for the time to the ſpirit of deluſion, in all things contrare to the true Chriſt our Sauiour the ſonne of God: for the true Chriſt is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to vs in holy Scripture, that if an Apoſtle or Angell from Heauen teach another Goſpell, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally<note place="margin">Gal. 1, 8.</note> about the perſon of Jeſus Chriſt, let him bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, as the Apoſtle ſayes. Well, then the Scripture giues vs to vnderſtand, that the true Chriſt hath aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 14 16.</note> euen our nature of the virgine Mary, Partaker of fleſh and blood, &amp; in ſubſtance &amp; properties like to vs in all things, except ſinne, who himſelfe hath giuen vs war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand to account of any obtruded in his name, as a falſe Chriſt. But the doctrine of the Maſſe drawes vs to a pretended Chriſt, the ſubſtance of whoſe bodie is made of the ſubſtance of bread, changed by the force of fiue latine wordes, ſaid by a Romiſh Prieſt, <hi>Hoc eſt enim corpus meum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly the true Chriſt his bodie is ſenſible, might be ſeene, touched, handled and felt, as ſenſibly as any mans body, not only before his death, when hee bare our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, but alſo after his reſurrection, when he had laide downe our infirmities: made vp of fleſh and bones, the verie ſame that hang vpon the croſſe, faſtned with nails as himſelfe teſtifies. <hi>Behold my hands and my feete that it</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 24. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>is I my ſelf, handle mee and ſee mee, for a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones as yee ſee mee to haue,</hi> ſayth hee, wherein hee giues vs all to vnderſtand that he wil not haue vs to think that hee hath another body or ſubſtance now after his reſurrection, than he had before his crucifying. Next to proue the veritie of his reall and corporall preſence he appeales to the true teſtimony of all their ſenſes, being
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17649:23"/> contented that they ſhuld not eſteem him bodily preſent, except they ſaw and felt him to haue fleſh and bones, but the Doctours of the Maſſe teach men to beleeue in, and to adore a Chriſt, whoſe body is borne vp betwixt the Prieſts finger and his thumbe, which neither can be ſeen nor felt, nor any wayes is ſenſible, a falſe Chriſt who may not abyde the proof and rule which the true Chriſt hath ſet downe in his word to try the trueth of his body and bodily preſence by.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the true Chriſt grew vp from a childe to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie ſtature of men before his death, and beeing dead his body took vp proportionall rowm in the Sepulchre, ſo that when hee was now riſen, the Linnings wherein his body was wrapped were found in the ſepulchre, ſome of them at the part where his feete lay, and ſome at the part where his head lay, and after his reſurrection hee ſhewed his hands and feete in the owne due propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diſtant one from another in place; but the Papiſts are made to worſhip a Chriſt in the Maſſe, whoſe head and feete and all the partes of his bodye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleet, are not only in the boundes of their paper-thin hoſtie, but in euerie preene poynt rowme of the ſame, for this is their expreſſe doctrine that, <hi>Corpus Chriſti eſt totum in tota hoſtiâ, &amp; totum in quolibet puncto,</hi> that the body of Chriſt is whole in the whole hoſtie, and whole in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie poynt or part thereof.</p>
               <p>Fourthlie, the true Chriſt will not haue vs to imagine of his body, that euer it was or ſhall bee in many places at one time, for when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and his mother ſought him three dayes, they could not find him till they came to the very place where only he was in the Temple diſputing with the doctours, when he was vpon the mount he was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17649:23"/> not bodilie any where elſe, when hee was on this ſide of the Sea, he was not on that ſide, when he was in the wilderneſſe, pinnacle of the Temple, in the ſhip, in the houſe, there he was and no where elſe, when he was in the graue his body was not riſen; and when hee roſe the Angell ſayeth of the graue he is not here, hee is riſen behold the place where the Lord lay, when hee was with his diſciples, he ſayes himſelfe hee was not aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, when hee aſcended, hee left his diſciples in regard of his bodilie preſence, not to come againe in bodily preſence vntill hee came to take them to that place which hee went to prepare for them, but theſe doctours tell vs that their Chriſt in whom they belieue, &amp; whom they command to be worſhipped hath a body which at an inſtant and poynt of time is in an hundreth places within a Church, and in fiue hundreth places of the ſame Church is not, in a word hath a body which is in as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſecrated hoſties as are in the World at one time though there will be thouſands dayly and which body is in no other place or ſpace betwixt the hoſties, and yet will avow that ſuch a body is but one ſingle, and the ſame body vndivided, which was borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and hang vpon the croſſe, ſo peart are they to hold vp their falſe Chriſt by calling him the true, when hee hath nothing of this trueth, that is in our Lord.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, the true Chriſt once died from his giuing vp the ghoſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe vntill his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but after that he dieth no more, but is aliue for euermore; he ſuffers no more bodily, his blood is ſhed no more, his ſoule no more ſeuered from his body, this is the Chriſt which the Scripture teaches vs to beleeue into, and to worſhip: but the Popiſh doctrine drawes theſe ſilly ſoules that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17649:24"/> beleeues them, to beleeue and adore ſuch a Chriſt whoſe verie ſubſtantiall body is bathed and ſwimmes in his owne naturall and true blood dayly: for when the Prieſt conſecrateth the chalice then the wine, as they ſay, is turned ſubſtantially in blood, as certainly &amp; really as Chriſt changed water into wine. Now when the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie is broken, and a part thereof put in the conſecrate chalice, among the verie blood as they teach, which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and every part thereof, as they ſay, doth containe the very body of Ieſus, doe I ſpeake any thing but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their doctrine, when I ſay that, that Chriſt of theirs ſwimmes dayly in his owne blood, incace they abide at their doctrine, teaching that Chriſts words in the Sacrament, are taken literally: for theſe words <hi>This is my body,</hi> taking the wordes literally, muſt haue ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe than theſe wordes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>This is my blood,</hi> and ſo the words beeing taken literally, as they pretend, the hoſtie being put in the cup, the body is put in the blood.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, the true and liuing Chriſt, where hee is bodily preſent, can walke alone, he needes not to be lifted, nor to bee borne, or carried in mens hands, he is not feared to fall, nor that any euill befall him. But the Romiſh Doctours, in effect (J muſt now ſay with griefe, decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers) drawe the people to adore for their Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, a Chriſt of the Prieſtes making in the Maſſe, who is ſo weake, that hee can not riſe till he bee lifted, hee can not walke but muſt bee carried, and when he is mounted vp in his makers hand, except his creator and maker hold him vp, or if the Prieſt himſelfe ſnap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and fall at a proceſſion, or in a journey, then this Chriſt goeth to the ground, and his maker both, and there he lyeth, though it were in a myre, till hee bee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17649:24"/> lifted againe. What care haue J ſeene taken to lift this Chriſt attentiuelie, and to lay him downe againe ſoftly, for feare of breaking of him? and if hee bee not eaten preſently, but muſt bee keeped to bee adored vpon the Altar, ſome dayes after, then euery night at euen hee is put in ward, and keeped faſt vnder locke and key or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarly, leſt while his maker and preſeruer is ſleeping the myce or the ratts, whom the Worlde can not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade, but the hoſtie is verie bread indeed, ſhould carry him away, and vſe ſome ſhort improbation againſt this their tranſubſtantiation: this can not bee but a matter of laughter to thoſe who are fred from the Romiſh yock, but alace for pittie of the Soules that beleeues all is well. I know they gull the people by telling them that Chriſt<note place="margin">Iohn. 20. 26.</note> came in to his Diſciples the doore beeing ſhut. And that this could not bee but by rarifying his owne ſubſtance to ſuch ſubtilitie that it might goe through the doore: but poore Soules that heareth this, they muſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute nor reply, but beleeue as the Church beleeues. If they would reply it were greater reaſon that the doore ſhould yeeld to Chriſt then hee to it, and that it were as eaſie for him to come in the chamber and the doore ſhut, before and after hee came in, keeping ſtill his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſubſtance in the owne naturall conſtitution, as it was to <hi>Peter</hi> to come through the priſon, and through the yron gate, which was ſhut before and after he came<note place="margin">Act. 12 10.</note> out, but opened when he went through: And no farder can this text affoord them: if any (J ſay) would replye after this manner this pretext would not ſaue them. They pleaſe the people another way alſo (for feare that this might bee anſwered) by diſtinction of a glorified body and vnglorified, for taking away whereof I ſay.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17649:25"/> Seuenthly, the true Chriſt his body is glorified with ſuch a glory as doth not aboliſh the ſubſtantiall proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his body, but only makes the ſame more illuſtrious and conſpicuous: whereof himſelfe gaue a proofe in his tranſfiguration, when hee clothed himſelfe with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the only begotten ſon of God for a while: at which time his glorie made not his body to diſappeare, but to appeare more conſpicuouſly than before. Another proof<note place="margin">Act. 9. 3. &amp; 26. 13.</note> hee gaue of this at the converſion of <hi>Paul</hi> when from Heauen there ſhined a light from him (while hee ſpake downe to <hi>Saul</hi>) brighter than the Sunne at noone day. and to put vs out of doubt in this matter, the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle<note place="margin">Philip. 3. 21.</note> ſayth that <hi>Chriſt ſhall change our vile bodies, and make them like to his owne glorious body.</hi> Wherein he lets vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, firſt, that our Lord ſtill retaines the ſame true body which hee aſſumed, and that his body is glorious and bewtifull. Next, hee ſhowes that Chriſt Jeſus hath ſuch a body now in Heauen as wee ſhall haue in our owne degre when the reſurrection comes: but when the reſurrection comes our bodyes fleſh and bones will riſe and bee glorified. Therefore our Lord hath ſuch a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in his owne degree of fleſh and bones glorified: from which glory now his body can not bee ſeuered. But that Chriſt which is made in the Maſſe, hath a body no ways glorious nor conſpicuous, but altogether ignominious, and ſubiect to moe perſonall diſgraces, then when hee ſuffered at Hieruſalem; as that which is ſaid already may cleare.</p>
               <p>Eightly, and laſt of all (to be ſhort) the true Chriſt hath forwarned vs not to beleeue any ſuch Chriſt after his aſcenſion as men ſhall poynt out on the Earth, ſaying of<note place="margin">Mat. 24 23.</note> him <hi>Loe heere, loe there is Chriſt, For there ſhall ariſe falſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17649:25"/> Chriſts and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo that if it were poſſible, they ſhould deceaue the very E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Behold I haue told you before, Wherefore if they ſhall ſay</hi>
                  <note place="margin">24.</note> 
                  <hi>to you, behold hee is in the deſert, goe not foorth, behold he is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">25.</note> 
                  <hi>in the ſecreete place, goe not foorth. For as the lightning com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">26.</note> 
                  <hi>out of the Eaſt, and ſhineth to the Weſt, ſo ſhall alſo the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">27.</note> 
                  <hi>comming of the ſonne of man bee.</hi> And again by his Apoſtle<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 2.</note> declares himſelf only to be fund in Heauen for his bodily preſence, diſcharging vs to ſet our affection vpon any thing on earth. But the Chriſt in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Papiſts Prieſts and doctors teaches people to belieue as their God, and to worſhip as their Sauiour, &amp; on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cauſe them ſet their affection, is corporally preſent in the earth, and his body on the earth all the dayes of the yeare: of whom my eares haue heard ſay times out of number, loe heere, loe there, loe yonder our Lord and Sauiour comming through the ſtreet, let vs goe and convoy him; and in the Maſſe the Prieſt lifts him vp, and after puts him in the peoples mouth, and hee goes ouer the throat. What be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of him then ye will ſay? heare what the true Chriſt ſayeth <hi>Perceiue you not that whatſoeuer entereth into the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math: 15. 17,</note> 
                  <hi>mouth goeth into the belly and is caſt out into the draught?</hi> O how farre then are the people deceiued! Firſt, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue they haue among their hands the true Chriſt, and doe worſhip him, when they worſhip only an Idoll and a falſe Chriſt. Next, they belieue that howeuer the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bee, that their intention to ſerue the true Chriſt will ſaue them from the ſinne, and the Iudgment due to ſuch a ſinne, and then they are againe deceaued: for if good intentions could haue any weight with God where the worke is not warrantable, then theſe men ſhould goe free, who murther the Prophets and ſeruants of Jeſus,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17649:26"/> thinking they do God good ſeruice; of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt ſpeaks<note place="margin">Ioh. 16. 2.</note> Then the Jewes ſhould goe free, who beleeued when they were pleading againſt Chriſt &amp; diſhonouring him, that they were friends to the promiſed Meſſias. The <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians</hi> beleeued that they held the true Chriſt when they joyned juſtification by works and faith together, and yet the Apoſtle tells them that if they held Chriſt ſo, <hi>Chriſt ſhuld not profite them.</hi> Jt was a miſconceaued Chriſt<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 2.</note> that deceiued the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Heretiques of old, for euery hereticke pretended an intention to honour the true Chriſt, and it is a falſe Chriſt that deceaueth the Jewes, who pretend that they are keeping their faith and worſhip to the true Meſſias promiſed, but haue forged in their owne braine one altogether different from the true, &amp; yet none of all theſe haue euer conceiued a Chriſt, more contrary to the true Chriſt, then is this forged Chriſt in the Maſſe. without warrand as is ſaid of Scripture, and contrare to the tenet of antiquitie, howeuer the Prieſts and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites gull their auditours with pretence of the ſame. For <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayeth <hi>Acceptum panem &amp; diſtributum diſcipulis</hi>
                  <note place="margin">lib. 4. ad verſus Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem cap. 40.</note> 
                  <hi>corpus ſuum illud fecit, hoc eſt corpus meum dicendo, id eſt, figura corporis mei.</hi> Chriſt tooke bread and gaue it to his diſciples making it his body, while hee ſayes This is my body, that is, a figure of my body: where ye ſee that this Father who liued two hundreth yeers after Chriſt doth expone theſe words of the inſtitution figuratiuely. And yet <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is not aſhamed to uſe this teſtimony for<note place="margin">lib. 3. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtiae cap. 20.</note> proouing tranſubſtantiation, but doth bewray heerein his fraud and deceitfull handling of the Fathers: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging this place ſo directly contrare him, hee leaueth out the Fathers gloſſe, that is, <hi>a figure of my bodie.</hi> And <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is ſo cleare in this matter, that it is a wonder
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17649:26"/> that any man ſhoulde oppoſe him for giuing a rule how to know when the words of holy Scripture are to be taken figuratiuely, &amp; when properly he ſayth thus, <hi>Si preceptiua loquutio eſt, aut flagitium aut facinus vetans, aut</hi>
                  <note place="margin">lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> doctrina chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na cap. 16</note> 
                  <hi>utilitatem, aut beneficentiam iubens, non eſt figurata, ſi autem flagitium aut facinus videtur iubere, aut vtilitatem, aut bene ficentiam vetare figurata eſt: niſi manducaueritis (inquit) carnem filii hominis, &amp; ſanguine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> biberitis non habebitis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam in vobis, facinus vel flagitium videtur iubere, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura eſt ergo.</hi> If the precept forbid any crime or wicked deede, or command any profite or beneficence then is it not figuratiue: but if it ſeeme to command any crime or wicked deed, or to forbid any profite or beneficence it is figuratiue, then doth he giue for inſtance to this rule theſe words of our Sauiour <hi>Except yee eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man and drink his blood yee haue no life in you,</hi> Theſe wordes ſayeth hee ſeeme to command ſome crime and wicked deed; therefore they are figuratiue. Many other paſſages of Fathers J might cite, but I feare to be too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, neither neede J to inſiſt much on Fathers ſeeing the very Canon of the Maſſe doth ouerthrow tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. For after the wordes of conſecration: the Prieſt offering Ieſus Chriſt to God, prayeth after this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Supra quae propitio ac ſereno vultu reſpic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re digneris ſicuti accepta babere dignatus es munera pueri tui iuſti</hi> Abell. On which things may it pleaſe thee to look with a good and fauourable countenance, and to accept of them, as thou did accept of the preſents of <hi>Abell</hi> thy righteous ſeruant. Any man may eaſily perceiue, that if there were nothing there but Chriſt as they affirme, the Prieſt durſt neuer take vpon him to be a interceſſour betwixt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the ſonne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as though the ſon had loſt the fauour
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17649:27"/> of his Father, for whoſe only ſake wee all are receaued in fauour.</p>
               <p>And ſince J haue now made mention of the Maſſe, J can not conceale what ſecreete reluctation was euer in my minde, euen when J was moſt bewitcht with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntments of Poperie, againſt their propitiatory ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice dayly offered vp in the Maſſe, which ſo flatly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts the words of Scripture <hi>With an offering hath he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 14. Verſ. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>for euer them that are ſanctified.</hi> And to exclude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iteration the Scripture ſayeth <hi>We are ſanctified by the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the body of Ieſus Chriſt once made.</hi> And moſt clearly <hi>As it is appoynted for euery man once to die &amp;c.</hi> Neither<note place="margin">Heb. 9, 27. 28.</note> will the diſtinction of a bloody and vnbloody ſacrifice ſatisfie this paſſage, ſeeing that the Apoſtle ſhowes that as a man dieth but once, ſo Chriſt is offered but once. How ridiculous a thing ſhould it bee for one to ſay, that a man can die but once a bloody death, but hee can die oftner an vnbloody death? and if this diſtinction of theirs can not hold in the death of man, neither can it in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of the Lord Jeſus. Seeing the Scripture preciſly compareth them in number that they are both but once. Yea, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>preſſe wordes of that ſame chapter the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture excluds this diſtinction while it ſayth <hi>Without ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>of blood there is no remiſſion of ſins.</hi> If then the Maſſe bee an vnbloody ſacrifice, by it there is no remiſſion of ſins. And leſt this ſhould be eluded by the typicall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of old, the Apoſtle ſpeakes in the preſent time &amp;c. And this much concerning their Maſſe, which was the ſecond part whereof I promiſed to ſpeake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17649:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Merites.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ollowes here the third part whereof J promiſed to ſpeak, which contains ſome of their common abſurdities, and firſt of Merites: for the mixture of our works, and the workes of Chriſt Ieſus is vntole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and more incompatible than the mixture of wine and water, for to make vp the blood<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of their Sauiour in the Maſſe: how can wee haue good workes before wee bee made good by regeneration? ſeeing an euill tree can not bring foorth good fruite. Yea, they are gone ſo farre on in this mixture, that they exclude Chriſts merites al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together from the formall cauſe of our iuſtification, and only makes Chriſts righteouſneſſe a helpe whereby we our ſelues may fully &amp; formally bee iuſtified before God <hi>Si quis dixerit homines iuſtificarivel ſola imputatione iuſtitiae</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Canone 10 &amp; 11 ſesſione 6 Concilii Trident.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſti, vel ſola peccatorum remiſſione, excluſa gratia &amp; chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate quae in cordibus eorum per ſpiritum ſanctum diffundatur, atque illis inhaereat, aut etiam gratiam qua iuſtificamur eſſe tantum fauorem Dei, anathema ſit.</hi> If any man ſay that wee are formally iuſtified by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt let him bee accurſed. &amp;c. Neither doth their doctrine ſtay heere, but proceeds to works of ſupererogation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they put God in their debt, and enrich the Pope by laying of theſe works of ſupererogation in his ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe to bee ſold out at his pleaſure for moneyes. Since theſe works can be applyed to men for their ſatiſfaction which they haue not wrought, wherfore may not the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Chriſt Jeſus be applyed to vs to our iuſtification? and as ſin althogh inherent into vs, and only imput vnto Chriſt Ieſus, who had no inherent ſin in him, made him
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17649:28"/> die the death wherefore may not Chriſts righteouſneſſe inherent in him and imput vnto vs bee accepted of God for our iuſtification to life, and that ſo much the more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt Ieſus is our head and cautioner, which the Saints are not, <hi>For he hath made him to be ſin for vs, which</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. cap 5. verſ. 21,</note> 
                  <hi>knew no ſin &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of taking away the Cup.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ouching their minching of the holy Sacrament of the Lords Table, and depriuing rhe People of the one halfe thereof, contrare to Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, who commanded them all to drinke of it, is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous defrauding of the people of their due comfort and that by <hi>Iohn</hi> 6, which they will haue ſpoken of the Sacrament, <hi>except yee eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>drink of his blood, yee haue no life in you.</hi> So to depriue them of the blood is to depriue them of eternall life. And in the primitiue times when perſecution raged in the Church the godly Fathers, neuer omitted the holy cup to the people, &amp; that not only becauſe of Chriſts divine inſtitution, but alſo that they might encourage people to ſhed their blood chearfully for him who had ſhed his blood for them, &amp; did ſo friely communicate with them in the holy cup. Further Chriſt ſayeth <hi>it is the cup of the new Teſtament in his blood, which he ſhed for the remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Then it appeareth that to depriue the people of the cup, is aſmuch as to depriue them of the blood of Chriſt for the remiſſion of their ſins: for in the hoſtie there is no ſhedding of blood, as they themſelues confes. As for the cuſtom of the primitiue Church, it is clear in this poynt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17649:28"/> neither can they or do they deny it; yet when either the command of Chriſt, or practiſe of the primitiue Church ſeemeth to croſſe their buſineſſe, they diſſalow both him and the ancients, and in open counſell giue a decreet to their contrare. The councill of Conſtance holden anno 406, which was the firſt councill that diſcharged the cup, as an hereſie, towardes the middeſt of the Canon<note place="margin">Concili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſe. 13. ſeſſ,</note> hath theſe wordes: <hi>Although Ieſus Chriſt did inſtitute and adminiſter to his Diſciples this venerable Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vnder the formes of bread and wine; and likewiſe although in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church this Sacrament was receaued by the faithfull vnder both kinds, neuertheleſſe this cuſtome hath with reaſon beene induced that it ſhould bee receaued by thoſe who conſecrate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both kynds, and by the layity vnder forme of bread only &amp;c.</hi> And concluds that theſe that would maintaine the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare were heretiques, where by conſequence they make Chriſt and the primitiue Church heretiques, at leaſt in practiſe, which if J had not red and conſidered in their councils, J could not haue beleeued that men could be ſo impudent and abſurd as to affirme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 14.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Images.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere J can not paſſe by their adoration of Jmages<note place="margin">2 book of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Saints chap. 21.</note> but muſt giue a taſte thereof. Their doctrine is of Images that they are not only <hi>relativè,</hi> as they reſpect the thing repreſented, but properly and <hi>perſe,</hi> by themſelfe, and terminatiuely without reſpect to the thing repreſented, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hath expreſly: yea, not only
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17649:29"/> with the worſhip of <hi>dulia</hi> or ſeruice as they call it (by the which diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they blind the eys of the ignorant, ſince all religious worſhip, in whatſoueer degrie belongs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to God) but alſo they teach and affirme that the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of God, and the croſſe ought to bee worſhipped, with the ſelfeſame ſupreme worſhip that is due to God himſelfe, which they call <hi>Latria:</hi> as hath expreſly their<note place="margin">25. queſ. 3. arti. in the concl. 4. article</note> Angelick doctour, in his third part <hi>Sic ergo dicendum eſt &amp;c.</hi> and fourth article in the concluſion <hi>Crux Chriſti &amp;c.</hi> which concluſion the foreſaid doctour prooues by this, that wee giue the ſupreme worſhip to him, in whom we put the hope of our ſafetie: but in the croſſe of Chriſt (This is the croſſe of wood whereon hee was nailed) we put our hope of ſafetie. So the Papiſts obiect of faith ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his doctrine, is an Image of ſtocke and ſtone. And therefore <hi>Suarez</hi> ſayes in expreſſe tearmes <hi>Per hanc</hi>
                  <note place="margin">45. diſp. 4. ſect.</note> 
                  <hi>adorationem, &amp;c.</hi> (I ſhall faithfully tranſlate the words) By this adoration a man not only profeſſeth that which hee adoreth to repreſent God, but alſo to bee God, and his ſupreme Lord and Redeemer; otherwiſe it would not be a true and ſupreme worſhip. The common people their caſe in this Idolatrie is deplorable; but ſomewhat more excuſable, albeit they be involued in that ſame guil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tineſſe, who muſt beleeue by an implicite faith, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer their Church beleeues: for their great doctours doe expreſly admoniſh their Readers, that their Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers let not the people vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in their ſermons, that this Soueraigne worſhip of God, ſhould bee giuen to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, by the principles of the Roman catholicke faith; for it might readily skarre them, &amp; of catholick Romans make them become Calviniſt hereticks. See <hi>Bellarmine</hi> of the Jmages of Saints at theſe words <hi>Quantum ad &amp;c,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">22. chap.</note>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17649:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> giues the ſame watchword in the place forſaid. And this<note place="margin">25. queſ. 54. diſ. 4. article</note> becauſe as they both acknowledge in the forſaid places, the common people can not be capable of theſe ſublime diſtinctions, wherby the foreſaid doctrine muſt be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: yea, skarſly ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> our great doctoures themſelues. Some of them for eſchueing the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this foreſaid doctrine do uſe theſe tearmes dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly and indirectly but any that pleaſeth to examine, at more length this defence they ſhal find it indirect enugh to giue to the creature any way a worſhip due to the Creator. Further for backing of this doctrine their beſt reaſon that I could perceiue they euer broght was, their blotting out of the ſecond command of the Lords Law. for giuing and not graunting that the ſecond command were one with the firſt, yet wherfore do they ſcrape out ſo great a part of that command, if their beſt defence ſtood not in cancelling the Law of God, which is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to their adoration of Jmages?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of their new beliefe, ſatiſfaction, purgatorie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this place their large addition to their beliefe repreſents it ſelfe to my mind: as may be ſeen in the bull of Pope <hi>Pitis</hi> the 4. concerning the oath taken of their Church-men containing their <hi>Trent</hi> creed wherein beſide the Articles of the Apoſtles creed, they haue ingroſſed many other Articles of their moſt groſſe and abſurde hereſies. I can not alſo omitte heere their idle repetition of Prayers, aſcrybing merite and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the number of them, for I my ſelf haue been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17649:30"/> to ſay ſuch a number of <hi>Aues, Pater noſters,</hi> by waye of pennance, or for the reliefe of Soules, and no fewer than theſe that were enioyned: For they teach that in baptiſm our ſins are forgiuen vs by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and ſatiſfaction of Chriſt allanerly, but the ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after baptiſme, be taken away and expiat by our own ſatisfactions: but the Apoſtle ſayth <hi>That as the wage ſin is death, ſo the gift of God is life eternall throgh Ieſus Chriſt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>our Lord.</hi> Heauen then is Gods free gift through Chriſt and not our deſeruing. Neither can it be conſidered how Chriſts obedience is properly a ſatisfaction, and yet ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requireth or admitteth our ſatisfaction. Beſids their owne extravagant fayth, that one drop of Chriſts blood is ſufficient to ſaue the whole World, what neceſſitie or place then is for our ſatisfaction in our Saluation. They will not receaue the Kingdom of Heaven after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but as a iuſt debt, to the which God of juſtice is bund and obliged to them, not only for the merits of Chriſt, but alſo for the merits of their owne works, which hath an equal worth anſwerable to the Kingdome of Heauen. J paſſe by here their ſelling of Maſſes, their baptiſing of Bells, baptiſm, being a Sacrament of the new couenant only, and no wayes belonging to ſenſleſſe creaturs: their ſcrotching fire of Purgatory, as hot as hell, wherein the Souls of the godly dying in the Lord, are tortured before they come to Heauen, till ſuch time as the puniſhment due to their veniall ſin, in that continuall torture bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And yet the Scritpure tels vs <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 14 13.</note> 
                  <hi>die in the Lord, for ſo ſayeth the Sprit, they reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and their works follow them.</hi> Fearefull ſhould their reſt bee, if dieing in the Lord, with ſome little thing vnſatisfied as they affirme, they ſhuld be caſt in the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17649:30"/> as hot as hells fire. And heere is to be obſerued the mercileſſe dealing of their father the Pope, who hauing power to relieue ſoules when he pleaſes, yet ſuffers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands to be tortured there ſtill, till he or his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue money for their deliuerance. And thus much ſhortly for the third part whereof I promiſed to ſpeake.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The cunning dealing of Romiſh Emiſsaries in ſeducing and diſputing.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow being forced here to acknowledge the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid falſe grounds of the Romiſh Religion, which in my miſcarying J laide downe as true, to haue beene the beginning of all this miſchiefe; and hauing my mind ouercharged with the filthineſſe and loathſomnes thereof, to teſtifie the vnfained forſaking of them, &amp; all the filthynes of their ſuperſtition: J muſt add ſome things by way of concluſion for the loue I carry to my Country &amp; the trueth of that Religion which is allowed of God, albeit J know it will incenſe ſundry againſt mee.</p>
               <p>I would aduertiſe young Schollers and others, whether at home or abroad, to bee warre of the Jeſuite his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dealing, with other their Emiſſaries ſuch as are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie Prieſts, Friers &amp;c. whether hee come directly to ſeduce you, or come occaſionally to diſput with you. If hee haue a purpoſe to ſeduce you, hee will firſt make choyſe of ſome catholicke of your acquaintance, who hath beſt credite of you; and moſt reſpected by you, him he will inſtruct how to handle you, and will put his owne ſpeaches and arguments in his mouth, if you hearken &amp;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17649:31"/> giue eare and make hopes you may bee theirs, an offer will bee made to you to ſpeak with a Father, or learned man, and ſo you and and he ſhall come to conference. If hee can not finde a fit perſon to deale with you, then hee will come openly to you if he be where he may profeſſe himſelfe: if not, he will come vnder the habite of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman or burgeſſe of a Towne, or Countryman, as beſt fits his purpoſe; &amp; as it were by occaſion falling in your company, will talke of any purpoſe till hee take you vp, and as he hath time to ſtay or to bee with you, ſo will he worke, ordinarily hee will blame all our profeſſours, for few good works and open euill liues of the great many: this at once he will turne vpon the Religion. But ſtumble not you for this: for the Religion of the Jewes was good when the Prophet complaines that <hi>Faith and trueth was</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>departed from the children of men.</hi> The Lords word which is our Religion, condemnes the ſins of profeſſours more than they can condemne the ſame. They will obiect the liues of Miniſters, what they pleaſe to ſpeak of them, and they haue in readineſſe ſome examples and inſtances in print or writ or in their memorie, but ſtumble not you at this, for they doe injurie to the Miniſters when they blame all for the fault of ſome: and again they doe iniury to Gods word, when they preaſe to blame the trueth for the teachers fault. One of the twelue Apoſtles was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill: what was the Apoſtles or the Apoſtleſhip the worſe? and yet when all is ſaid, if their cloſters were as open as Miniſters converſation, they ſhould mak litle talke in this poynt. They will tell thee of the ignorance and want of Learning among Miniſters, be not you troubled for this, they are learned enough that know Ieſus Chriſt rightly, and can teach him ſoundly, learning is not the glory of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17649:31"/> our Religion but trueth: and yet thogh I ſomtime thoght ſo, and ſaid ſo as they doe, yet I found it otherwiſe when I mette with the Miniſters. Yocke with the Miniſters when they will, ſo farre as J know they will ruſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf litle for the want of learning. They will obiect they haue no warrandable calling, but vrge you them to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the calling of their chiefe pillars, Popes, Cardinals and Prelates, whoſe office and entrie in their office God neuer ordained in his worde. Miniſters calling goes not by ſucceſſion, but by election. Their office is preſcrived in the word, their entrie and qualification: Let euery one juſtifie as he is challanged, ſo much as may bee ſeene of men is alwayes nearer the rule of the Apoſtles than any of their calling. They will obiect the noveltie of this Religion, and will aske for ſucceſſion of Paſtours in our Church. But anſwer you, that they ſlander you vniuſtly for novelty, whoſe doctrin was taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and recommended to after ages. Where the Catholick Church and true ſheep of Chriſt vvho heard his voyce and fled ſequeſtrating themſelues from ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were, there was our Church, particular profeſſours names is no poynt of ſaluation. What manamong ten thouſand can ſhew his naturall pedegree from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth generation? ſhal a man be queſtioned of the trueth of his humanity if he cannot deduce his genealogie from <hi>Adam</hi> or <hi>Noah?</hi> Albeit the Proteſtants can bee able to ſhow continuance of their doctrine by the lyne, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of the witneſſes the truth through all ages, from Chriſts vnto our time. If this obiection were of any worth, wee might uſe it againſt their Church, and they could not deduce from Chriſt or the Apoſtles time, or a long time after any that euer heard of a number of the Articles of their Faith. But this is one of their ſhiftes to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17649:32"/> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about genealogies, and generalities, leſt comming to particulars the ſtrength of our cauſe and weakneſſe of theirs ſhould appeare. They will obiect <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvine,</hi> and our firſt reformers were Papiſts firſt: But it makes not to vs, wee belieue not any poynt of Religion upon their worde, but what wee finde aggrieing with Scripture. Againe <hi>Paul</hi> was not the worſe Apoſtle that ſometime hee was a Phariſee, but their Religion is ſo much the worſe as ſuch men and many after them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooued to quite it, or loſe their Soules. They will obiect diuerſities of opinions, and diuiſions, and ſchiſmes, but anſwere you; that there were diviſions in the Churchs of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> and other Apoſtolicke Churches: and yet they were not the leſſe true Churches: let euery Church anſwere for her ſelfe, whether ſhee keepe vnitie with Chriſt and his Apoſtles in her doctrine: for vnitie without trueth is but conſpiracie in errour. It is a who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh impudencie to obiect vncleannes to a chaſt Matron, they might remember Chriſts aduertiſment <hi>Hypocrite caſt out the beame of thy owne eye firſt:</hi> or the Poets admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Loripedem rectus derideat.</hi> For beſide the bloody ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of their Popes, and the irreconciliable diuiſions of their Doctours, the Jeſuites and Dominicans, at this day do iarre ſo hotly concerning grace and frie wil, that their Pope darre not determine the queſtion for feare he loſe one of the parties. Jf they finde you ignorant they will cauſe you belieue that your Miniſters teaches ſuch and ſuch hereſies, as that they are enemies to good works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> enemies to the Virgine Mary, and to the Saintes, that they giue libertie to ſinne, and makes God the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it, that ſuch a writer on our Religion hath ſuch a blaſphemous errour in ſuch a book, and another writer,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17649:32"/> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blaſphemie in another booke; <hi>Luther</hi> ſayes this, and <hi>Caluine</hi> ſayes that, and a thouſand ſlanders ſuchlike. To bee ſhort, their whole wits they will imploy to brangle you, in ſome generall, that they may haue you at an van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, brought ouer to their grounds, whereof they will make great ſhow and oſtentation, or if they condeſcend vpon a particular, and finde you therin weak, they will ſhoote at all. But if yee keepe the loue of the Scriptures, the Lord ſhall mak you to ſtand, <hi>Great peace haue they who</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 165.</note> 
                  <hi>loue thy Law, and nothing ſhall offend them.</hi> As for their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puts, they will make great boaſt and brag if they ſee not a learned partie: if they finde a learned partie, they will take them to diſcourſe if they may: if they muſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put they will keepe the former method, that is, ſtick vpon generalls, about the viſibilitie of a Church, and notes as they ſay thereof, whether the true Church can erre, and will hold off whether <hi>Rome</hi> can erre as long as they can: they wil make ſhew to quot councils and Fathers, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they can obtaine the victory by them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the books are rare, and few are acquaint with them to know whether they ſay right or wrong: they wil avow forged diſtinctions, when they are preſt, and flee to phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophick tearms, not becaus ſuch refuges wil ſaue them, but becauſe by this meanes they blovv miſt in their eyes that cannot follovv them to their lurking holes: vvhen their cauſe is vveakeſt then they grovv boldeſt, and vvill ſet a brovv vpon their part, that their countenance may giue vveight to their vvatter-vverſh argument or anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvers: vvhen they are like to ſuccumb, they will cry lovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and caſt in a nevv ſubiect to diſput on: yee will not put them to ſilence, albeit they knovv they are ouercome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17649:33"/> For what by ſhifts, what by ſubtilities: what by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, what by apparent verities, they can colour their cauſe, though neuer ſo bad.</p>
               <p>It vvere an endles labour to ſhovv all their courſes &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſible, theſe may ſuffice to giue aduertiſement to you, who may bee in danger, that you acquaint you with the grounds of your owne Religion, and diligently read the Scriptures: that you bee not raſh to vndertake a diſput concerning Religion, and leane not much to your owne or others diſputation: for in a diſput yee will get the two diſputers wits tried, and acquaintance with their owne grounds which they defend, but yee will not ſo try Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it is the ſtudieing of all the grounds thereof, and trying them by the Scripture muſt make you ſure: when Gods glory or others edification requires that you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put, doe it adviſedly, for they haue their ſet arguments, and their writen diſputs, carrying about with them: ſet the ſtate of the queſtion right, limite thy argument to be brought on either ſide to Scripture, or reaſons deduced therefrom: not becauſe thou needſt to feare any councils and fathers, but partly becauſe fathers and councills are but human teſtimonies, partlie becauſe if you goe from the Scriptures, ye goe to the long Sands, and the diſput will not end ſhortlie, and ſo hee eſcapes and his errour is not convinced, and the auditours is left ſuſpenſe. This much may ſerue for a generall aduertiſment. Now for my part, pray for mee, that God may ſhow more and more mercie on mee. J know many a bitter hard word will be ſpoken againſt me, &amp; J deſerue them all, not for my departing from them, but for my firſt revolting in my ignorant youthead from this Religion whereinto I am
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17649:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> now brought home by Gods mercie, his name be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for euer. And the Lord make known this his trueth to the World, vvho knovves it not; and no doubt mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituds ſhal come vnto the Lord &amp; this Religion, vvhich is grounded on his trueth, as Doves flocking to their vvindovves.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Lord doe it for Chriſts ſake. All glorie bee giuen to God through Chriſt.
<signed>Yours in Chriſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> PATRIK CRAVFURD.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>Pag. 10 for Chap 5 read Chap 4. Page 47 line 8 for juſtification read regeneration. Page 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> line 1. at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning read <hi>Suarez,</hi> The changes of letters or tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of vvords the courteous reader vvill tolerate.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
